AHSAN ANIS

Toronto, Canada 🔾 (365) 996 5625 🍙 ahsananis@alumni.iu.edu 庙 www.linkedin.com/in/aanis 🍙 www.aanis.github.io

DATA SCIENCE • DATA ANALYSIS • BUSINESS INTELLIGENCE • MACHINE LEARNING

SUMMARY

Experienced at applying algorithmic, statistical and quantitative techniques to big datasets to identify patterns, trends and forecasts. Demonstrated ability to **improve business performance**, **generate revenue** and **reduce costs** by designing and implementing methodologies to define, measure and analyze data. Applies strong organizational and managerial skills for timely preparation and delivery of machine learning algorithms, business intelligence dashboards, data-driven recommendations and reports. A quick learner who applies new ideas for engineering features and products and has experience working for and managing data science teams.

SKILLS

Programming: SQL, Python

ML Frameworks: Tensorflow, Keras, Scikit-Learn Database: MySQL, Teradata, BigQuery, Azure BI: Tableau, PowerBI, Looker, Google Data Studio

Packages: Pandas, NumPy, Altair, Matplotlib, NetworkX Algorithms: Regression, Classification, Neural Nets Analytics: A/B Testing, Time Series Forecasting, Metrics Management: Strategy, Leadership, Team Building

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Recce Studio, Principal Data Scientist, Toronto, Canada

March 2019 - Present

- **Product Management:** Used Agile methodology to successfully conceive, design and develop a data science application that lets the user perform data science without coding.
- Data Analysis: Developed data analysis module that seamlessly extracts, transforms, loads (ETL) and imputes structured and unstructured data using python's data analysis and manipulation package for the preparation of reports and models.
- Data Visualization: Designed data visualization module that utilizes python's open source visualization library to render graphs, charts and plots for business intelligence (BI).
- Machine Learning: Developed regression and classification algorithms using python's machine learning (ML) package that can run on either binary or textual data for predictive analytics.

Punjab Information Technology Board, Data Scientist, Lahore, Pakistan

June 2016 - March 2019

- Crime Prediction System: Created crime classification algorithm using artificial neural nets in Tensorflow and Keras to
 predict crime from various crime categories with an overall accuracy of 80%. The recommendation algorithm provides 3-hour
 patrolling schedules for law enforcement agencies reducing crime by 33.33%. Designed Tableau dashboard that visualizes
 crime clusters on a map and shows daily, weekly, monthly and yearly historical patterns by granularity.
- World Bank Big Data Dashboard: Created and maintained Tableau dashboards for real-time reporting for a multi-million dollar World Bank project dealing with big data of private and public school systems. Successfully conducted workshops to train and facilitate the handover of the developed system to the analysts at the Department of Education.
- Call Data Records Analytics: Performed social network analysis (SNA) on millions of call data records using custom SQL
 queries in Teradata database, python's graph library NetworkX and Gephi network analysis and visualization software to
 identify call details, hidden network patterns and crime clusters. Trained law enforcement agents to use the developed CDR
 techniques to solve crimes.
- Social Media Metadata Collection: Developed, tested and maintained an algorithm to mine real-time social media data by geo-location for 1.26 million users. The project was specifically designed to include keyword search and sentiment analysis of all data mined using python's library for neuro-linguistic programming (NLP).
- Face Detection and Recognition System: Developed a face recognition system that detects, recognizes and matches human faces using face recognition API. The face recognition system was created to identify and match driving license and national identity card profiles of 110 million people to prevent fraud and identity theft.

En Pointe Technologies, Data Analyst, Los Angeles, USA

June 2011 - May 2015

- Data Automation: Collected Microsoft software assets using automated software discovery tools saving \$100,000/year.
- Data Transformation: Used ETL to clean, organize and archive inventory of customer software licenses in MySQL database.
- Data Analysis: Analyzed customer unique needs using SQL queries and prepared reports for Microsoft's audit in MS Excel.
- Revenue Generation: Leveraged Microsoft licensing certifications to help the team achieve \$30 million in revenue generation.

EDUCATION

California State University Fullerton, Fullerton, USA Master of Science in Information Systems, Business Analytics April 2016